<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "+//IDN docutils.sourceforge.net//DTD Docutils Generic//EN//XML" "http://docutils.sourceforge.net/docs/ref/docutils.dtd">
<!-- Generated by Docutils 0.13.1 -->
<document dupnames="common\ misunderstandings" ids="common-misunderstandings" source="&lt;string&gt;" title="Common Misunderstandings"><title>Common Misunderstandings</title><subtitle dupnames="common\ misunderstandings" ids="id1">Common Misunderstandings</subtitle><comment xml:space="preserve">This file is part of the OpenDSA eTextbook project. See</comment><comment xml:space="preserve">http://algoviz.org/OpenDSA for more details.</comment><comment xml:space="preserve">Copyright (c) 2012-2016 by the OpenDSA Project Contributors, and</comment><comment xml:space="preserve">distributed under an MIT open source license.</comment><raw format="xml" xml:space="preserve"><avmetadata>null</avmetadata></raw><raw format="xml" xml:space="preserve"><odsalink>AV/AlgAnal/MisunderstandingsGraphCON.css</odsalink></raw><paragraph><title_reference>Asymptotic analysis &lt;asymptotic analysis&gt;</title_reference> is one of the most
intellectually difficult topics that undergraduate computer science
majors are confronted with.
Most people find <title_reference>growth rates &lt;growth rate&gt;</title_reference> and asymptotic
analysis confusing and so develop misconceptions about either the
concepts or the terminology.
It helps to know what the standard points of confusion are,
in hopes of avoiding them.</paragraph><paragraph>One problem with differentiating the concepts of
<title_reference>upper &lt;upper bound&gt;</title_reference> and <title_reference>lower bounds &lt;lower bound&gt;</title_reference> is
that, for most algorithms that you will encounter, it is
easy to recognize the true growth rate for that algorithm.
Given complete knowledge about a cost function, the upper and lower
bound for that cost function are always the same.
Thus, the distinction between an upper and a lower bound is only
worthwhile when you have incomplete knowledge about the thing being
measured.
If this distinction is still not clear,
then you should <title_reference>read about analyzing problems &lt;AnalProblem&gt;</title_reference>.
We use <title_reference>Theta</title_reference>-notation to indicate that there is no meaningful
difference between what we know about the growth rates of the upper
and lower bound (which is usually the case for simple algorithms).</paragraph><paragraph>It is a common mistake to confuse the concepts of upper bound or
lower bound on the one hand, and <title_reference>worst case</title_reference> or
<title_reference>best case</title_reference> on the other.
The best, worst, or <title_reference>average cases &lt;average case&gt;</title_reference> each
<strong>define a cost</strong> for a specific input instance
(or specific set of instances for the average case).
In contrast, upper and lower bounds describe our understanding of the
<strong>growth rate</strong> for that cost measure.
So to define the growth rate for an algorithm or problem, we need to
determine what we are measuring (the best, worst, or average case) and
also our description for what we know about the growth rate of that
cost measure (big-Oh, <title_reference>Omega</title_reference>, or <title_reference>Theta</title_reference>).</paragraph><paragraph>The upper bound for an algorithm is not the same as the worst case for
that algorithm for a given input of size <title_reference>n</title_reference>.
What is being bounded is not the actual cost (which you can
determine for a given value of <title_reference>n</title_reference>), but rather the
<strong>growth rate</strong> for the cost.
There cannot be a growth rate for a single point, such as a particular
value of <title_reference>n</title_reference>.
The growth <strong>rate</strong> applies to the <strong>change</strong> in cost as a
<strong>change</strong> in input size occurs.
Likewise, the lower bound is not the same as the best case for a given
size <title_reference>n</title_reference>.</paragraph><paragraph>Another common misconception is thinking that the best case for an
algorithm occurs when the input size is as small as possible, or that
the worst case occurs when the input size is as large as possible.
What is correct is that best- and worse-case instances exist for
each possible size of input.
That is, for all inputs of a given size, say <title_reference>i</title_reference>,
one (or more) of the inputs of size <title_reference>i</title_reference> is the best and one
(or more) of the inputs of size <title_reference>i</title_reference> is the worst.
Often (but not always!), we can characterize the best input case for
an arbitrary size, and we can characterize the worst input case for an
arbitrary size.
Ideally, we can determine the growth rate for the characterized best,
worst, and average cases as the input size grows.</paragraph><topic><title>Example</title><paragraph>What is the growth rate of the best case for sequential search?
For any array of size <title_reference>n</title_reference>, the best case occurs when the
value we are looking for appears in the first position of the
array.
This is true regardless of the size of the array.
Thus, the best case (for arbitrary size <title_reference>n</title_reference>) occurs when the
desired value is in the first of <title_reference>n</title_reference> positions, and its cost
is 1.
It is <emphasis>not</emphasis> correct to say that the best case occurs when
<title_reference>n=1</title_reference>.</paragraph></topic><raw format="xml" xml:space="preserve"><inlineav
    type="ss"
    exer_name="MisunderstandingsGraphCON"
    long_name="MisunderstandingsGraphCON"
    points="0"
    required="True"
    threshold="1.0">
</inlineav>
</raw><raw format="xml" xml:space="preserve"><avembed
    type="ka"
    exer_name="MisSumm"
    long_name="MisSumm"
    points="1.0"
    required="True"
    threshold="5">
</avembed>
</raw><raw format="xml" xml:space="preserve"><odsascript>AV/AlgAnal/MisunderstandingsGraphCON.js</odsascript></raw></document>