<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "+//IDN docutils.sourceforge.net//DTD Docutils Generic//EN//XML" "http://docutils.sourceforge.net/docs/ref/docutils.dtd">
<!-- Generated by Docutils 0.13.1 -->
<document ids="balanced-trees" names="balanced\ trees" source="&lt;string&gt;" title="Balanced Trees"><title>Balanced Trees</title><comment xml:space="preserve">This file is part of the OpenDSA eTextbook project. See</comment><comment xml:space="preserve">http://algoviz.org/OpenDSA for more details.</comment><comment xml:space="preserve">Copyright (c) 2012-2013 by the OpenDSA Project Contributors, and</comment><comment xml:space="preserve">distributed under an MIT open source license.</comment><raw format="xml" xml:space="preserve"><avmetadata>null</avmetadata></raw><raw format="xml" xml:space="preserve"><odsalink>AV/Development/treeIndexingCON.css</odsalink></raw><paragraph>The <title_reference>Binary Search Tree &lt;BST&gt; &lt;BST&gt;</title_reference> has a serious deficiency for
practical use as a search structure.
That is the fact that it can easily become unbalanced, so that some
nodes are deep in the tree.
In fact, it is possible for a BST with <title_reference>n</title_reference> nodes to have a depth
of <title_reference>n</title_reference>, making it no faster to search in the worst case than a
linked list.
If we could keep the tree balanced in some way, then search cost would
only be <title_reference>Theta(log n)</title_reference>, a huge improvement.</paragraph><paragraph>One solution to this problem is to adopt another search
tree structure instead of using a BST at all.
An example of such an alternative tree structure is the
<title_reference>2-3 Tree &lt;2-3 Tree&gt; &lt;TwoThreeTree&gt;</title_reference>
or the <title_reference>B-Tree &lt;B-tree&gt; &lt;BTree&gt;</title_reference>.
But another alternative would be to modify the BST access functions in
some way to guarantee that the tree performs well.
This is an appealing concept, and the concept works well for heaps,
whose access functions maintain the heap in the shape of a complete
binary tree.
Unfortunately, the heap keeps its balanced shape at the cost of weaker
restrictions on the relative values of a node and its children, making
it a bad search structure.
And requiring that the BST always be in the shape of a
complete binary tree requires excessive modification to the tree
during update, as we see in this example.</paragraph><target refid="balancebst"></target><raw format="xml" ids="balancebst" names="balancebst" xml:space="preserve"><odsafig>null</odsafig></raw><paragraph>If we are willing to weaken the balance requirements, we can come up
with alternative update routines that perform well both in terms of
cost for the update and in balance for the resulting tree structure.
The <title_reference>AVL tree &lt;AVL Tree&gt; &lt;AVL&gt;</title_reference>
works in this way, using insertion and deletion routines
altered from those of the BST to ensure that, for every node, the
depths of the left and right subtrees differ by at most one.</paragraph><paragraph>A different approach to improving the performance of the BST is to
not require that the tree always be balanced, but rather to expend
some effort toward making the BST more balanced every time it
is accessed.
This is a little like the idea of path compression used by the
<title_reference>UNION/FIND algorithm &lt;UNION/FIND&gt; &lt;UnionFind&gt;</title_reference>.
One example of such a compromise is called the
<title_reference>splay tree &lt;Splay Tree&gt; &lt;Splay&gt;</title_reference>.</paragraph><paragraph>The <title_reference>Red-Black Tree &lt;Red-Black Tree&gt; &lt;RedBlack&gt;</title_reference> is also a binary
tree, but it uses a different balancing mechanism.</paragraph></document>