<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "+//IDN docutils.sourceforge.net//DTD Docutils Generic//EN//XML" "http://docutils.sourceforge.net/docs/ref/docutils.dtd">
<!-- Generated by Docutils 0.13.1 -->
<document ids="comparison-of-list-implementations" names="comparison\ of\ list\ implementations" source="&lt;string&gt;" title="Comparison of List Implementations"><title>Comparison of List Implementations</title><comment xml:space="preserve">This file is part of the OpenDSA eTextbook project. See</comment><comment xml:space="preserve">http://algoviz.org/OpenDSA for more details.</comment><comment xml:space="preserve">Copyright (c) 2012-2016 by the OpenDSA Project Contributors, and</comment><comment xml:space="preserve">distributed under an MIT open source license.</comment><raw format="xml" xml:space="preserve"><avmetadata>null</avmetadata></raw><section ids="space-comparison" names="space\ comparison"><title>Space Comparison</title><paragraph>Now that you have seen two substantially different implementations for
lists, it is natural to ask which is better.
In particular, if you must implement a list for some task,
which implementation should you choose?</paragraph><paragraph>Given a collection of elements to store, they take up some amount of
space whether they are simple integers or large objects with many
fields.
Any container data structure like a list then requires some additional
space to organize the elements being stored.
This additional space is called <title_reference>overhead</title_reference>.</paragraph><paragraph><title_reference>Array-based lists &lt;array-based list&gt;</title_reference> have the disadvantage
that their size must be predetermined before the array can be
allocated.
Array-based lists cannot grow beyond their predetermined size.
Whenever the list contains only a few elements, a
substantial amount of space might be tied up in a largely empty array.
This empty space is the overhead required by the array-based list.
<title_reference>Linked lists &lt;linked list&gt;</title_reference> have the advantage that they only
need space for the objects actually on the list.
There is no limit to the number of elements on a linked list,
as long as there is <title_reference>free store</title_reference> memory available.
The amount of space required by a linked list is <math>\Theta(n)</math>,
while the space required by the array-based list implementation is
<math>\Omega(n)</math>, but can be greater.</paragraph><paragraph>Array-based lists have the advantage that there is no wasted
space for an individual element.
Linked lists require that an extra pointer for the <literal>next</literal> field be
added to every list node.
So the linked list has these <literal>next</literal> pointers as overhead.
If the element size is small, then the overhead for
links can be a significant fraction of the total storage.
When the array for the array-based list is completely filled, there
is no wasted space, and so no overhead.
The array-based list will then be more space efficient, by a
constant factor, than the linked implementation.</paragraph><paragraph>A simple formula can be used to determine whether the array-based list
or the linked list implementation will be more space efficient in a
particular situation.
Call <math>n</math> the number of elements currently in the list,
<math>P</math> the size of a pointer in storage units
(typically four bytes), <math>E</math> the size of a data element in
storage units (this could be anything, from one bit for a Boolean
variable on up to thousands of bytes or more for complex records),
and <math>D</math> the maximum number of list elements that can be stored
in the array.
The amount of space required for the array-based list is <math>DE</math>,
regardless of the number of elements actually stored in the list at
any given time.
The amount of space required for the linked list is <math>n(P + E)</math>.
The smaller of these expressions for a given value <math>n</math>
determines the more space-efficient implementation for <math>n</math>
elements.
In general, the linked implementation requires less space than the
array-based implementation when relatively few elements are in the
list.
Conversely, the array-based implementation becomes more space
efficient when the array is close to full.
Using the equation, we can solve for <math>n</math> to determine the
<title_reference>break-even point</title_reference> beyond which the array-based implementation
is more space efficient in any particular situation.
This occurs when</paragraph><math_block xml:space="preserve">n &gt; DE/(P + E).</math_block><paragraph>If <math>P = E</math>, then the break-even point is at <math>D/2</math>.
This would happen if the element field is either a four-byte
<literal>int</literal> value or a pointer, and the <literal>next</literal> field is a typical
four-byte pointer.
That is, the array-based implementation would be more efficient (if
the link field and the element field are the same size) whenever the
array is more than half full.</paragraph><paragraph>As a rule of thumb, linked lists are more space efficient when
implementing lists whose number of elements varies widely or is
unknown.
Array-based lists are generally more space efficient when
the user knows in advance approximately how large the list will
become, and can be confident that the list will never grow beyond a
certain limit.</paragraph><raw format="xml" xml:space="preserve"><avembed
    type="ka"
    exer_name="ListOverhead"
    long_name="ListOverhead"
    points="1.0"
    required="True"
    threshold="5">
</avembed>
</raw></section><section ids="time-comparison" names="time\ comparison"><title>Time Comparison</title><paragraph>Array-based lists are faster for access by position.
Positions can easily be adjusted forwards or backwards by
the <literal>next</literal> and <literal>prev</literal> methods.
These operations always take <math>\Theta(1)</math> time.
In contrast, singly linked lists have no explicit access to the
previous element, and access by position requires that we march
down the list from the front (or the current position) to the
specified position.
Both of these operations require <math>\Theta(n)</math> time in the average
and worst cases, if we assume that each position on the list is
equally likely to be accessed on any call to <literal>prev</literal> or
<literal>moveToPos</literal>.</paragraph><paragraph>Given a pointer to a suitable location in the list,
the <literal>insert</literal> and <literal>remove</literal> methods for linked lists
require only <math>\Theta(1)</math> time.
Array-based lists must shift the remainder of the list up or down
within the array.
This requires <math>\Theta(n)</math> time in the average and worst cases.
For many applications, the time to insert and delete elements
dominates all other operations.
For this reason, linked lists are often preferred to array-based
lists.</paragraph><paragraph>When implementing the array-based list, an implementor could
allow the size of the array to grow and shrink depending on the number
of elements that are actually stored.
This data structure is known as a <title_reference>dynamic array</title_reference>.
For example, both the Java and C++/STL <literal>Vector</literal> classes implement a
dynamic array,
and JavaScript arrays are always dynamic.
Dynamic arrays allow the programmer to get around the limitation on
the traditional array that its size cannot be changed once the array
has been created.
This also means that space need not be allocated to the dynamic array
until it is to be used.
The disadvantage of this approach is that it takes time to deal
with space adjustments on the array.
Each time the array grows in size, its contents must be copied.
A good implementation of the dynamic array will grow and shrink
the array in such a way as to keep the overall cost for a series of
insert/delete operations relatively inexpensive, even though an
occasional insert/delete operation might be expensive.
A simple rule of thumb is to double the size of the array when it
becomes full, and to cut the array size in half when it becomes one
quarter full.
To analyze the overall cost of dynamic array operations over time,
we need to use a technique known as
<title_reference>amortized analysis &lt;amortized analysis&gt; &lt;AmortAnal&gt;</title_reference>.</paragraph><section ids="practice-questions" names="practice\ questions"><title>Practice Questions</title><raw format="xml" xml:space="preserve"><avembed
    type="ka"
    exer_name="LLSumm"
    long_name="LLSumm"
    points="1.0"
    required="True"
    threshold="5">
</avembed>
</raw></section></section></document>