<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "+//IDN docutils.sourceforge.net//DTD Docutils Generic//EN//XML" "http://docutils.sourceforge.net/docs/ref/docutils.dtd">
<!-- Generated by Docutils 0.13.1 -->
<document dupnames="implementing\ tree\ traversals" ids="implementing-tree-traversals" source="&lt;string&gt;" title="Implementing Tree Traversals"><title>Implementing Tree Traversals</title><comment xml:space="preserve">This file is part of the OpenDSA eTextbook project. See</comment><comment xml:space="preserve">http://algoviz.org/OpenDSA for more details.</comment><comment xml:space="preserve">Copyright (c) 2012-2016 by the OpenDSA Project Contributors, and</comment><comment xml:space="preserve">distributed under an MIT open source license.</comment><raw format="xml" xml:space="preserve"><avmetadata>null</avmetadata></raw><section dupnames="implementing\ tree\ traversals" ids="id1"><title>Implementing Tree Traversals</title><paragraph>Recall that any recursive function requires the following:</paragraph><block_quote><enumerated_list enumtype="arabic" prefix="" suffix="."><list_item><paragraph>The base case and its action.</paragraph></list_item><list_item><paragraph>The recursive case and its action.</paragraph></list_item></enumerated_list></block_quote><paragraph>In this module, we will talk about some details related to correctly
and clearly implementing recursive tree traversals.</paragraph><section ids="base-case" names="base\ case"><title>Base Case</title><paragraph>In binary tree traversals, most often the base case is to check if we
have an empty tree.
A common mistake is to check the child pointers of the current node,
and only make the recursive call for a non-null child.</paragraph><paragraph>Recall the basic preorder traversal function.</paragraph><raw format="xml" xml:space="preserve"><codeinclude>null</codeinclude></raw><paragraph>Here is an alternate design for the preorder traversal, in which the
left and right pointers of the current node are checked so that the
recursive call is made only on non-empty children.</paragraph><raw format="xml" xml:space="preserve"><codeinclude>null</codeinclude></raw><paragraph>At first it might appear that <literal>preorder2</literal> is more efficient
than <literal>preorder</literal>, because it makes only half as many recursive
calls (since it won't try to call on a null pointer).
On the other hand, <literal>preorder2</literal> must access the left and right
child pointers twice as often.
The net result is that there is no performance improvement.</paragraph><paragraph>Perhaps the writer of <literal>preorder2</literal> wants to protect against the case
where the root is <literal>null</literal>.
But <literal>preorder2</literal> has an error.
While <literal>preorder2</literal> insures that no recursive
calls will be made on empty subtrees, it will fail if the orignal call
from outside passes in a null pointer.
This would occur if the original tree is empty.
Since an empty tree is a legitimate input to the initial call on the
function, there is no safe way to avoid this case.
So it is necessary that the first thing you do on a binary tree
traversal is to check that the root is not <literal>null</literal>.
If we try to fix <literal>preorder2</literal> by adding this test, then making the
tests on the children is completely redundant because the pointer will
be checked again in the recursive call.</paragraph><paragraph>The design of <literal>preorder2</literal> is inferior to
that of <literal>preorder</literal> for a deeper reason as well.
Looking at the children to see if they are <literal>null</literal> means that we are
worrying too much about something that can be dealt with just as well
by the children.
This makes the function more complex, which can become a real problem
for more complex tree structures.
Even in the relatively simple <literal>preorder2</literal> function, we had to write
two tests for <literal>null</literal> rather than the one needed by <literal>preorder</literal>.
This makes it more complicated than the original version.
The key issue is that it is much easier to write a recursive function
on a tree when we only think about the needs of the current node.
Whenever we can, we want to let the children take care of themselves.
In this case, we care that the current node is not <literal>null</literal>, and we care
about how to invoke the recursion on the children, but we do <strong>not</strong>
have to care about how or when that is done.</paragraph></section><section ids="the-recursive-call" names="the\ recursive\ call"><title>The Recursive Call</title><paragraph>The secret to success when writing a recursive function is to not
worry about how the recursive call works.
Just accept that it will work correctly.
One aspect of this principle is not to worry about checking your
children when you don't need to.
You should only look at the values of your children if you need to
know those values in order to compute some property of the current
node.
Child values should not be used to decide whether to call them
recursviely.
Make the call, and let their own base case handle it.</paragraph><topic><title>Example</title><paragraph>Consider the problem of incrementing the value for each node in a
binary tree.
The following solution has an error, since it does redundant
manipulation to left and the right children of each node.</paragraph><raw format="xml" xml:space="preserve"><codeinclude>null</codeinclude></raw><paragraph>The efficient solution should not explicitly set the children
values that way.
Changing the value of a node does not depend on the child values.
So the function should simply increment the root value, and make
recursive calls on the children.</paragraph></topic><paragraph>In rare problems, you might need to explicitly check if the children
are null or access the children values for each node.
For example, you might need to check if all nodes in a tree satisfy
the property that each node stores the sum of its left and right
children.
In this situation you must look at the values of the children to
decide something about the current node.
You do <strong>not</strong> look at the children to decide whether to make a recursive
call.</paragraph></section></section><section ids="binary-tree-increment-by-one-exercise" names="binary\ tree\ increment\ by\ one\ exercise"><title>Binary Tree Increment By One Exercise</title><raw format="xml" xml:space="preserve"><extertool
    resource_name='Binary Tree Increment By One Exercise'
    resource_type="external_assignment"
    learning_tool="code-workout"
    points="1">
</extertool>
</raw></section></document>